Finding Aid for the Hyung-ju Ahn Collection of Korean Materials, 1902-1959
Hyung-ju Ahn Collection of Korean Materials,
1902-1959
368
Ahn, Hyung-ju
10 boxes (5 linear ft.) 1 oversize box
University of California, Los Angeles. Library Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Hyung-ju (also known as Henry) Ahn graduated from the Wharton School of Finance and Commerce at the University of Pennsylvania in 1964, worked as a computer systems analyst for aerospace companies and for Orange County, California (1965-95), and received his MA in history from California State University, Fullerton. He wrote his thesis on Korean interpreters at Japanese-American internment camps during World War II. The collection contains mostly Korean printed materials, including religion and history books, and textbooks published under Japanese occupation. Also contains an original documentary motion picture film, Mugunghwa Tongsan (Hibiscus Garden), about the Korean community in Hawaii from 1900-47.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Advance notice required for access.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Hyung-ju Ahn, 1997.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 4230300
Biography
Hyung-ju (also known as Henry) Ahn was born in Seoul, Korea; attended Seoul National University for two years; came to Honolulu, Hawaii in 1957 and then Reedley, California a few years later; graduated from the Wharton School of Finance and Commerce at the University of Pennsylvania in 1964; worked as a computer systems analyst for aerospace companies and for Orange County, California from 1965-95; MA in history from California State University, Fullerton; wrote his thesis on Korean interpreters at Japanese-American internment camps during World War II.
Biographical Narrative
Hyung-ju Ahn [Korean characters], or Henry Ahn, was born in Seoul and attended Seoul National University for two years. In 1957 he came to Honolulu where his paternal grandfather, Reverend Chang-ho Ahn [Korean characters], had been a minister since 1926 at the Korean Methodist churches in Wahiawa, Oahu and in Honolulu. A Couple of years later, he joined his maternal grandparents, Mr. and Mrs. Charles Ho Kim [Korean characters] in Reedley, California. Charles Ho Kim had come to the United States in 1914 and his wife came 35 years later.
Hyung-ju Ahn graduated from the Wharton School of Finance and Commerce at the University of Pennsylvania in 1964. From 1965 to 1995, he worked as a computer systems analyst for aerospace companies and the County of Orange. He also earned a Master of Arts degree in history from California State University, Fullerton. His second master's thesis was “the Korean Interpreters at Japanese Alien Detention Centers During World War II.”
Beginning in 1987, Hyung-ju Ahn visited his relatives to interview and to collect Korean American primary source materials. He interviewed his great-aunt in Detroit, whose late husband, C.C. Ahn [Korean characters], came to Honolulu in January 1903 on the first shipload of Korean to come to Hawaii to work on sugar plantations. He also interviewed his grand-aunt in Hilo, Hawaii, whose father was an elder brother of C.C. Ahn and had sailed with him to Hawaii. Hyung-ju visited many historic Korean American sites and surveyed primary source materials including newsreels, home movies, documentary films, photographs, documents, audio recordings, and unpublished manuscripts written both in Korean and English.
Scope and Content
Collection contains mostly Korean printed materials, including religion and history books, and textbooks published under Japanese occupation. Includes 1902 passport, Korean Bible, fiction works, and a 1919 Korean Provisional Government savings bond issued in 1919. Also contains an original documentary motion picture film, Mugunghwa Tongsan (Hibiscus Garden), about the Korean community in Hawaii from 1900-47.
Expanded Scope and Content
The Hyung-ju Ahn Archival Collection consists of his great-uncle's passport issued to him by the Korean Imperial Government in 1902 to allow him to emigrate to Hawaii; his great uncle's Korean Bible and Korean fiction works; textbooks published in Hawaii and the Mainland United States for Korean language schools; textbooks published in Korea prior to 1910; a one-hundred dollar Korean Provisional Government savings bond issued in 1919; textbooks published in Korea under Japanese rule, which were used at the Korean Central School [Korean characters] in Honolulu in the 1920s; and the thirty-minute documentary film on the Korean American community in Hawaii entitled “Mugunghwa tongsan” [[Korean characters] Hibiscus Garden], which was directed by his father in 1947.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Books and documents on Korean Independence Movement and Korean Immigrant History (Box 1).
Books published under Korean imperial government (Box 2).
Textbooks published under Japanese rule (Box 3).
Books on religion (Box 4).
General history books (Boxes 5-6).
Chinese language books (Boxes 7-8).
Miscellaneous books (Boxes 9-10).
Film, Mugunghwa Tongsan (Hibiscus Garden), 1947 (Box 11).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Ahn, Hyung-ju--Archives.; Korea--Civilization--Archival resources.
Related Material
Korean American Oral History Project (Collection 1414). Available at the UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library.
Container List
- Books and Documents on Korean Independence Movement and Korean Immigrant History
  - Korean Imperial Government Special Passport, 1903. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Korean Provisional Government $100 Savings Bond Receipt, 1919., (Copy). (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Pak Únsik [Korean characters], “Hanguk t'ongsa” [Korean characters] Translated by Kim Pyóngsik [Korean characters]. Honolulu, 1917. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Kim Yóngu [Korean characters], “Toklip hyóljóngi” [Korean characters]. Honolulu, 1919. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Pak Únsik [Korean characters], “Hanguk toklip undong chi hyólsa” [Korean characters]. Shanghai, 1920 (In Chinese). (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Warren Y. Kim [Korean characters], “Haebang chosón” [Korean characters]. Los Angeles, 1948. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Textbooks of Economics, Biology, and Criminal Law, 1900s., (3 items). (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Books Published Under Korean Imperial Government
  - Korean History, 1900s., (3 items). (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Japanese History, 1900s., (1 item). (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - World History, 1900s., (2 items). (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Geography, 1900s., (3 items). (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Korean Reader, 1900s., (2 items). (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Textbooks, 1900s., (3 items). (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Textbooks Published Under Japanese Rule
  - Korean Reader, 1920s-1930s., (5 items). (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Chinese and Japanese Reader, 1909, 1937., (3 items). (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Japanese History and Geography, 1930s, (3 items).; (In Japanese). (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bible, 1912., (1 item). (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Books on Religion
  - Christian Books, 1908, 1912., (3 items). (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Christian Books, 1911., (2 items). (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Christian Books, 1924, 1938., (2 items). (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Bible, 1906., (1 item). (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Publications, ca. 1910s., (3 items). (Box 4, Folder 5)
- General History Books
  - Biographies of Great Korean Historic Figures: “Wiinjón” [Korean characters], 1920s., (4 items). (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - “Wiinjón,” 1937., (1 item). (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - “Wiinjón,” 1948., (2 items). (Box 5, Folder 3)
- General History Books
  - “Wiinjón,” 1950s., (3 items). (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - History of Wars in Korea, 1928., (1 item). (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - General Korean History., (2 items). (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - World Christian History, 1938., (1 item). (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Chinese-Language Books
  - “Sohak” [Korean characters], 1928., (2 items). (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - “Taehak” [Korean characters], 1927 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- “Non-ó” [Korean characters], 1927
  - Classical Poetry., (3 items). (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Classical Poetry., (2 items). (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Chinese-Language Books
  - Classical Writing., (2 items). (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - “Hunmin chóngÚm,” [Korean characters], Seoul, 1946, (Classical Reading)., (2 items). (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Chinese-Korean Dictionary., (1 item). (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous Books
  - Korean Language and Stories, 1910s-1920s., (3 items). (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - South Korean Elementary School Music Textbooks, 1969-1970., (3 items). (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Publications., (2 items). (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Publications., (2 items). (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - “Economic Report on Defeated Japan,” Unpublished English Material, ca. 1946. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Chinese-Japanese Dictionary., (1 item). (Box 10)
- “Mugunghwa tongsan,” [Korean characters] Hibiscus Garden, 1947. (Box 11)
  30-minute Documentary Film on a Korean Community in Hawaii.